<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in S. Peters Church at West-Chester the XXV. of September, 1586 Containing matter fit for the time: by Edward Hutchins Maister of Arts, and fellowe of Brazennose College.</title>
            <author>Hutchins, Edward, 1558?-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104320</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840058</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4529</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4529)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 250:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in S. Peters Church at West-Chester the XXV. of September, 1586 Containing matter fit for the time: by Edward Hutchins Maister of Arts, and fellowe of Brazennose College.</title>
                  <author>Hutchins, Edward, 1558?-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, and are to be sold in Pauls Church-yarde [by T. Cooke, London] at the signe of the Tygers head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1586]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B (-B8).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at West-chester.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4529:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4529:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN S. PETERS CHVRCH AT WEST-CHESTER THE XXV. <hi>OF SEPTEMBER,</hi> 1586. CONTAINING MATTER <hi>FIT FOR THE TIME:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Edward Hutchins Maiſter of Arts, and Fellowe of Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zennoſe College.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALME 74.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O deliuer not the ſoule of thy turtle-doue vnto the multitude of enimies. <bibl>verſ. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Ariſe O God, maintaine thine owne cauſe. <bibl>verſ. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inted by <hi>IOSEPH BARNES,</hi> and are to be ſold in Pauls Church-yarde at the ſigne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Tygers head.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4529:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4529:2"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>O THE WOORSHIPFVLL MAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ROGER PVLESTON Eſquire, grace <hi>and peace in Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough there be in Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on numbers of ſuch as haue &amp; do caſt off their riches into the Lordes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eaſurie: ſuch as are euerie waie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reful &amp; able to disburſe their two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence committed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng of the wounded man in Ierico: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe labours or rather almes are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orious on earth &amp; written in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en: though I knowe my ſelfe to be one of them, not worth any riches, at onelie a mite, rather wiſhing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue, then hauing to beſtow the two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce of God, yet haue I bin (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re, ſo now again) by entreaty won beſtow this ſhort ſermon, though
<pb facs="tcp:4529:3"/>
it bee but a mite: though nothing to that, which others caſt into the trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſury. Whereof therefore as of all deſire fauorable acceptation, ſo o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your worſhippe I am to craue it, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue bin bold, &amp; yet of dut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bound to offer the ſame, as a true though a ſmal toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my dutiful &amp; thankfull reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of your ſun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drie benefits towards me from tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to time, which the lord god requit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> where I cannot: who double &amp; mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiplie his bleſsings vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you &amp; kee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you in al your waies, and vs from thoſe enemies that ſtudie nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but how to diſquiet vs. AMEN</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips in Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> to commaund,</hi> E. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4529:3"/>
            <head>It is written in the 5. Chapter of Saint Pauls Epiſtle to the Galathians, &amp; 12. verſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>I would to God they were cut off that doe diſquiet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S SAINT PAVL (RIGHT</hi> Worſhipful &amp; dearly beloued in our deare ſauiour) was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of God, to be his lampe, &amp; a light of his golden Candel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke; ſo did hee performe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utie of light: he bent himſelfe to lighten them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat were in darckneſſe, whereſoeuer he came. Hee was a lamp to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> a lamp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> a lamp to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amp to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> a lamp to the <hi>Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns:</hi> to omit the reſt, hee was a lampe to theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople of <hi>Galatia,</hi> as appeareth by this Epiſtle which he penned firſt (as many take it) and firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherein appeareth that he had laied the skilful builder, &amp; laid them on chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e corner ſtone of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple: called &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem from fooliſhneſſe to wiſedome; from ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orance to knowledge; from error to the truth; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om ſuperſtition to chriſtian religion. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eit where by his painfull care, &amp; careful tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them, he had thus brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ppy eſtate in Ieſus Chriſt, it grieued Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to ſee it, &amp; therefore hee buſied himſelfe to
<pb facs="tcp:4529:4"/>
put out the cleare light of <hi>Paul</hi> the lampe of Chriſt our ſauior, &amp; to pull out of the wall the liuely ſtones that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> his elect builder had laid vpon him. Nay alas, he did not only grieue at this proſperous eſtate of theſe <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> wherein they ſtood; &amp; therefore ſent out ſuch as ſhould ſeek to ouerthrow the good that <hi>Paul</hi> had wrought among them: but as hee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, ſo hee tempted; and by his tempting preuailed ſo far, that the <hi>Galathians</hi> fell from light to darcknes; from true wiſedome to their former folly; from truth to error; from the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerity of religion to ſuperſtition; from chriſt to <hi>Moſes:</hi> by which meanes it came to paſſe that S. <hi>Paul</hi> their Apoſtle was in a maner forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and his truth almoſt forſaken of them, and among them. Which their miſerable eſtate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> piteous the Apoſtle conſidering, hee tooke thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> courſe to write this epiſtle to them; thereby to warne them of their eſtate by him in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell; of their folly in reuolting; of his care to conuert them again from conciſion to the true circumciſion: from the ceremonies of the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the truth of the goſpel, that ſo Ieſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> might profit them, and hee bee a ioyful Apoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ouer, &amp; in them. Many waies doth he moue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I neede not to expreſſe the ſpecials. In th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> verſe he layeth before him the miſchief, &amp; grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4529:4"/>
euill that the falſe Apoſtles wrought in the church, how they were enimies to the eſtate of theſe <hi>Galathians:</hi> how they brought them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the breade of life to feede on leauen: from the greene tree, to the dry ſticke; from the body to the ſhadow: from the kernell to the ſhell: from Chriſt to the Law ceremoniall: whereby they made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſore where they were healed: ſlaues where they were freed: loſt where they were before quitte by the goſpell of grace, and made Chriſt vnprofitable vnto them: where they fought well before, yet now to flee; where they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anne wel before, yet now to ſtand: where they were in the ſpirit, yet nowe to end in the fleſhe: where they had, yet nowe to looſe the faith of Chriſt our ſauiour. Which their miſerable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ition the Apoſtle pondering w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> himſelfe, how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttended to their deſtruction, &amp; to the diſglory of God: (whoſe goſpell was deſpiſed that way for vntrueth, and the blood of Chriſt was like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o bee of no profite vnto them) it did ſo grieue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im on the one ſide to ſee their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teous eſtate, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eale on the other ſide did ſo eate him vp, to ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he glorious goſpel of peace ſo trod in the duſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he burſt out in theſe words which I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead vnto you, Would to god they were cut off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat ſo diſquiet you, as if he ſhuld haue ſaid: O <hi>Galathians,</hi> I begot you in the faith, &amp; ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:4529:5"/>
be your father: I brought you to the light, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould bee your ſtarre: I haue taught you the truth, and ſhould be your maſter: and whereas the Church is an eſpouſed virgin to one huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 11.2.</note> &amp; that one husband is Ieſus Chriſt, the King of Kings, the God of all glory, I am the Bridegromes friend, (and ſo you ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute mee) that haue brought you to the ſpouſe, your mother the Church, in the Kings priuie cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber.<note place="margin">Cant. 1.3.</note> I haue brought you as <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,<note place="margin">Cant. 1.11.</note> to ſee the King at his repaſt, &amp; your ſpike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard hath giuen the ſmell thereof. O <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> what ſhal I ſay? I had an office: I prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my ſelfe to performe it: yea I laide before you a veſſell ful of the pretious blood of Chriſt to the purging of you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſins: nay I haue taken the pains to waſh you therein, as whit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as euer was the ſnow in <hi>Salmon:</hi> in a word, I haue deſcribed Chriſt before you, and preached him only a free and full Ieſus vnto you: yet and it was my ioie to ſee the happie fruites of theſe my labors among you: that you were become the Lambes of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 10. Cant. 2.1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phe. 5.23.</note> and Chriſt your ſheepheard: the leaues of Chriſt, and chriſt the Lilly: the members of the bodie of Chriſt, and Chriſt your heade: the inheritaunce of Chriſt and Chriſt your Lord, and gracious Sauiour But yet alas my deare <hi>Galathians</hi> what ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:4529:5"/>
ſaie? Where you were my ſonnes,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.19.</note> now yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e baſtardes: where you were light, now yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e dark: where you were in the truth, now yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſtraie:<note place="margin">Gal. 5.8.</note> where you were with the ſpouſe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e kings priuie chamber, now ye are out: your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ikenard now doth giue no ſmel therof. O my <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alathians</hi> therefore what ſhall I ſaie? The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oxe hath plaied the crafty part among you: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e falſe Apoſtles haue deceaued &amp; bewitched <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u: they haue broken the quiet league that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u had with God in Chriſt his onelie Sonne our deare Sauiour.<note place="margin">Gal. 2.1.</note> Oh my dear <hi>Galathians</hi> therefore I woulde to God they were cut off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at doe diſquiet you: for it pittieth my heart ſee the cockle ſo to hurt my corne: to ſee the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auen ſo to ſowre the lump of my good dough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at I had among you:<note place="margin">Gal. 5.9.</note> to ſee the falſe Apoſtls circumciſion (indeede the authors of conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on) by their falſe and perilous perſuaſion to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t you off from Chriſt the tree of life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ye did grow. O my dear <hi>Galathians</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re I woulde to God they were cut off that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us diſquiet you. This I take to be the whole nor of this Apoſtolick wiſh: wherein I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to your godlie conſideration, firſt, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles tender affection towardes the people <hi>Galatia:</hi> 2 I note a difficultie concerning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s affection: 3. I note the eſtate and condition
<pb facs="tcp:4529:6"/>
of al falſe Prophets and Apoſtles: and laſtly ſhort application of all. Touching the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> point,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Part.</note> the Apoſtles affection howe tender was and deeply ſet vpon theſe people of <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia,</hi> the whole Epiſtle beareth ſtrong witne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and euident proofe. So that how, &amp; how pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully he trauelled to teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I ſhal not ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to tel you: how carefull he was that way, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtate whereunto he had brought them doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſufficient tokens. Onely this, to labour make them Chriſtians: nay indeede to bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them to the eſtate of Chriſtians: to be do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and to feede on no graine but the wheat: to be Eagles, and to praie vpon no fleſh but of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Lamb: to thirſt and to drinke of no well but Chriſt the wel of God,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.13.14. &amp; 5.13.</note> the well of the water life: where they were loſt ſheep, to ſeek the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſeek the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as to find the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: being found to cloſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the fold of Chriſt, our Sauiour, this Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles loue was great that did ſo louinglie t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uel for them, but this was not al: for he did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> onely thus take care to bring them to the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt our Sauior,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.11</note> but to keep them in: n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not onely that, but where the Diuel had plai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the crafty Fox, and got them out of the foul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.2.</note> and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fed them: not with truth, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with error: with circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: not with chriſt with conciſion rather then circumciſion:<note place="margin">Gal. 5.4.</note> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed
<pb facs="tcp:4529:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with gal, not with hony: with poyſon, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith the ſweet bread of life: he tooke the pains <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> labour againe in their behalfe, and to reduce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em to the fould from whence they were got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n. His hearts deſire was that they might not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe the profit of their godly and good profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on, but that they might return and haue por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, and profite togither with him in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous paſſion of Chriſt, which yet theſe falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles went about to make of none effect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And though he might haue turned his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auel another way, for this their vnthankful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uolt from Chriſt the way, the trueth, &amp; life, hereunto hee had brought them: yet did hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t: but as hee had beene a mother to them, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nceaue them, to trauell for them, to bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em foorth to Chriſt:<note place="margin">Gal. 4.19.</note> ſo did hee not ceaſe as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>other to trauel againe and again, that chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight a newe bee framed in them, where they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by folly and falſe ſubtilty of the falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es loſt the very beuty of chriſt whereunto he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In which his trauel becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e falſe Apoſtles did greatlie trauel to hinder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m and them: therefore euen of meere zeale to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ods glorie and their ſaluation he brake into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is louing wiſh: O <hi>Galathians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I woulde to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od they were cutte off that doe diſquiet you: which woordes doe argue a tender intireneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4529:7"/>
of the Apoſtle ouer them: as that hee wiſh their health where they were wounded, the recall where they had ſtraied, their returne the truth which they had receiued by him:<note place="margin">Gal. 5.7.</note> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo their eſtate might be ſure, and their ſalua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on yea and Amen in Chriſt Ieſus, who could not otherwiſe profit them.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.4. 2. Part.</note> But here it wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> demaunded what the Apoſtle meaneth thus burſt out into ſo vehement a wiſh as here he ſeth? For it maie be thought more meet for Apoſtolike ſpirit to confute then to curſe: to ſoft then thus ſharp: rather to pity his enemy then to pray thus againſt them, would to G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they were cut off that do diſquiet you. Wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unto I aunſwere, that indeed many take th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wordes of the Apoſtle to be not againſt, but the behalfe of the falſe Apoſtls: as that Sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> doeth not wiſh their hurt, but their g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therein: that as they had taught circumciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before, and by that meanes ſtopt the people <hi>Galatia</hi> from their godly courſe which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had begun in chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.7.</note> and thereby did daunger theirs and their own ſoules, ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might now at length be cut off from that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perilous dealing, and called to the light of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> goſpell of chriſt, that ſo the <hi>Galathians</hi> mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be no more diſquieted, nor their eſtate any l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger endaungered: ſo that they will haue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4529:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rds of the Apoſtle to be ful of loue &amp; tender <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ection, not only towardes the <hi>Galathians,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſe caſe hee moſt pittied, but alſo towardes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> falſe Apoſtls, whoſe conuerſion he alſo wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d. And indeede I graunt the Apoſtles wiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uld haue bin, that theſe falſe Apoſtles might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue reclaimed their erronious and damnable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>xture of circumciſion with the Goſpel. And doubt not but his tender heart did ſo tender <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaluation of ſoules, that hee could haue wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d them, and could haue been hartily glad to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue ſeen them &amp; theſe people of <hi>Galatia,</hi> both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gether cut off from this their falſe perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d dangerous: Nay I am perſuaded that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could haue fallen out more to his ioy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſeene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altogether, as corn growing one fielde, as flowers floriſhing in one gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n, as branches bearing grapes in one vine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> knit together in the eye of Ieſus Chriſt, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e white or apple of the ſame: but yet wher he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w before his eyes the pittious ſtate wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Galathians</hi> ſtoode, and how the falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s had buſied themſelues to bring them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>to, and how they ſought by al means, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to make, but to continue them as dogges,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.17. Gal. 6.12.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here they were once the darlings: as thorns, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here they were once lillies: ſtrangers, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey were once near: idle, where they once ran
<pb facs="tcp:4529:8"/>
well:<note place="margin">Gal. 5 7. Gal. 3.1. Gal. 3.3.</note> fools where they were once wiſe: fleſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> where they were once ſpiritual, and gaue ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vnto the ſpirit, that not onely ſaid it: but cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and proclaimed it in their heartes, that God Chriſt was onely and wholy, fully and freel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Abba, father vnto them: whereby his darlin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was like to be deuoured: his lilly in <hi>Galatia</hi> be torne,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.11.</note> his owne crowne &amp; glory to be take from him, and Gods glorie to lie in the duſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo greeued him that hee burſt out and ſaide, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would to God they were cut off that ſo diſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>et you. Wherein he hath principally reſpect Gods glorie: ſecondarily to the happy and ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſtate of theſe <hi>Galathians:</hi> and thirdly to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> proſperous recouery of his labors among th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which becauſe they were greatly hindered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the meanes of theſe falſe Apoſtles, therefore burſt out euen of zeal and ſaid thus: O would to God &amp;c. In which woordes (to come to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> point) the Apoſtle yet breaketh not the bond charity, but keepeth it, in that he thus wiſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not of priuate affection, but in reſpect of God glorie, his church and congregation, which had in <hi>Galatia</hi> planted happily, &amp; yet the fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Apoſtles ſought to deſtroy moſt craftily.<note place="margin">Gal. 4.15.</note> No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wher euil is wiſhed to the droſſe, that the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be pure: euil to the chaffe, that the whea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may be fanned: euil to the leaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the dou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4529:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y be ſweet: euil to the pitch, that the cleane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y be clean: euile to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tare, that the corn may ſafe: euil to the wolfe that the ſheep may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a word to wiſh euil to the diuel &amp; to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rites &amp; falſe Apoſtles, that the glory of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y be glorious &amp; the church of god redeemed danger of them: zeal it is, euil zeal it cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut very chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the loue of god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraineth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the loue that is due to the church of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h beg &amp; craue it. Neither indeed do I take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe woordes of the Apoſtle, to bee ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ordes of euill wiſh to his aduerſaries, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rds of good wil to the people of <hi>Galatia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.10.</note> for much as he doth not wiſh them euill ſimply, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in reſpect, becauſe they did trouble the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urch, hinder &amp; hurt her in her race: becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y did diſquiet her. So that in reſpect of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lathians,</hi> whoſe ſafety was dear vnto him: whoſe ſaluation Gods glory had bin glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, in whoſe reuolt from the truth &amp; continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e therein, the falſe Apoſtles had ſtopt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſe of the glory of God, and brought their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to piteous caſe: (conſidering that it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many dogs ſhould die the death, then one dareling of Ieſus Chriſt, much more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſo many as were in <hi>Galatia</hi>) hee might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly &amp; did godly break out into theſe wordes
<pb facs="tcp:4529:9"/>
and ſay, <hi>ô</hi> would to God they were cut off t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do diſquiet you.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Wherein wee may ſee both what he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſheth to the falſe Apoſtles &amp; therin their eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as alſo the cauſe of his wiſh. He wiſheth t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were cut off: cut off from the people of <hi>Gala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> cut off from the company of them: cut off fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the number of Chriſtians: nay cut off vtterl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> curſed euerlaſtingly, before they ſhould bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch goodly plants, as he had planted, <hi>Apol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had watered, and God himſelfe had bleſſed <hi>Galatia.</hi> O terrible wiſh to proceede from Apoſtle, to wiſh their death and damnation yet <hi>ô</hi> wiſh no leſſe iuſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terrible: iuſt to v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the barren fig tree a curſe:<note place="margin">Mat. 21.16. Luc. 16.2. Pſ. 1.4.</note> iuſt to wiſh the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſteward a reckoning: iuſt to wiſh fire for ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble: iuſt to wiſh wind to ſcatter the chaffe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that not ſimply, but in reſpect: leaſt the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> trees of the lord, leaſt the children of his ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> leaſt his corne that grewe in <hi>Galatia</hi> ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> take any hurt. For that was the cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Apoſtle did ſo wiſh vnto them, becauſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſquieted them. Which is the third n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wherein if you aſke me wherein they did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> quiet them, the whole Epiſtle beareth wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> They did diſquiet them,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> becauſe they brou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them in doubt of his Apoſtleſhippe: diſq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> becauſe they taught a contrary doctr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4529:9"/>
to him: diſquiet them,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.7.</note> beecauſe they did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſuffer them to inioy the trueth that hee had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen them: diſquiet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they by ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eans had brought them from faith to works,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.21. Gal. 5.3 13. Luc. 2.14. Ephe. 2.17.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m grace to the law, from Chriſt to ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, from liberty to bondage, from the peace conſcience in Ieſu Chriſt the true and only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace of God, to ſeeke it in circumciſion, if not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, yet with the goſpel iointly: whereby they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de Chriſt Ieſus (who is and will bee in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tter of ſaluation either al in al, or nothing all) no way profitable vnto them: in a word, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y did diſquiet them, becauſe they by ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ans tooke the peace of conſcience from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But to come to an application of al: dearely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oued in our ſauior chriſt Ieſu, as theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Galatia</hi> had their <hi>Paul,</hi> by whoſe labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s preaching they did attain to the knowlege God the father in Chriſt his dearly beloued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne, ſo haue you, and with you, the people of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our land not wanted, but inioyed the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efite theſe many yeares, nay where you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re withered branches, yet <hi>Paul</hi> hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; where you were ready to wither againe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> againe, yet <hi>Apollo</hi> hath watered, and god <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bleſſed you with heauenly knowlege: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> know it, and I hope you al thanke god for that we haue beene cloudes and haue giuen
<pb facs="tcp:4529:10"/>
forth the dew: candles &amp; haue giuen forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> light: the breſtes of the ſpouſe and haue offer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> milcke: her teeth and haue diuided the <hi>Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the meat:<note place="margin">Cant. 4.11.</note> her tongs and haue ſpoken (as <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſpeakes) no leſſe than the very hunny heauen vnto you: and the Lord our God is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> witneſſe how we haue traueled in euery pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be fruitfull wombes vnto him among yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you your ſelues eaſily can, and I hope for yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> parts wil thankefully witneſſe, how wee h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beene voices, and what we haue cried: how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> haue beene hands, and what we haue labor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how we haue bin feete of, and for the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus, and how wee haue ſtoode in this, and ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like places to deliuer out the gladſom tidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of heauenly peace vnto you: nay more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we haue beene writing theſe many years (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſweetely figure out the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter) we thanke the liuing,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.2.</note> and our moſt lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, that wee haue written a faire and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Epiſtle among you: ſo that all the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> runne and reade, not the name of ſuperſtit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and ſuperſtitious deuotion, but of trueth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtian knowledge, &amp; religion in your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heads. You are the ſeales of our labours, are our crowne, and glory, and therein we glory:<note place="margin">Luc. 13.34.</note> to heare Chriſt our henne clocking, you as chriſtians following: to ſee you wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4529:10"/>
fould of chriſt, &amp; chriſt your ſheepherd: to ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cornes of chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſe of life:<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> to ſee you cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the knowlege of the truth to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent to it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome thus to hear it, that you may continue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> how it ioyeth our hartes? But alas though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bee our ioy &amp; happineſſe, to ſee you in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r happy eſtate; &amp; nothing could more glad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſee the branch abide in the vine: yet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath had &amp; yet hath his are abroad, wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot only hacks, but hopes to hew down the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch of chriſt in diuerſe places. Nay as it was <hi>Galatia,</hi> ſo hath it bin &amp; ſo it is now in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d:</hi> God grant that it be not: or (if it be not) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay not be ſo among you. For ſata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his your proſperous eſtate in Ieſu Chriſt, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not ſpared almoſt in euery place, euery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ouerthrow it. For what the powers of world haue don in this cauſe, I need not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ember you: &amp; what his falſe Apoſtles haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of late &amp; yet do atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, you are not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y you knowe what diuels haue come vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhape of Angels: What <hi>Eſaus</hi> vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of <hi>Iacob:</hi> What cutthroats vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of Catholicks: What <hi>Iudaſes</hi> vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of Ieſus: And that, not onely to corrupt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but alſo ſo far to diſquiet you, as to ſucke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery blood of Prince &amp; people among you, were posſible. By which means, it is come
<pb facs="tcp:4529:11"/>
to paſſe that the ſhip of Chriſt is not only da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed with waues, but in a maner ouerwhelm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and his ſheepe not onely purſued, but alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> quite deuoured in many places: as was t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore, ſo is our <hi>Galatia</hi> troubled. Nay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſies</hi> to the diſquieting of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> church Apoſtolicke wan <hi>Iudas</hi> from chriſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſauiour,<note place="margin">Ioh. 18.2.3.</note> and of an Apoſtle made him an A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtata.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> Theſe falſe Apoſtles bewitched th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Galathians,</hi> and made them fools: where t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were in the way to runne out: they went ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by their mixture of circumciſion with the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.4.</note> to make the goſpel of Chriſt fruitles v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them. Oh would to God <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> were not in this our land: <hi>ô</hi> would to God t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no familiars had plaid by their means the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Iudas</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt our ſauiour, <hi>ô</hi> would to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that many <hi>Galathians</hi> that runne wel, had beene ſtaied &amp; ſtopt from the good courſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had begun. But alas we want not in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> day the man that plaieth <hi>Iudas:</hi> nay alas vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the name of Ieſus, they haue beene and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt vs, that haue ſought and doe ſeeke their falſe perſwaſion to make the true C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian a <hi>Iudas:</hi> nay alas they doe it in diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> places already: and euen yet they ſpare no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uel to make you al Apoſtataes. They ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> abide to ſee you come to theſe our congreg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4529:11"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not abide to ſee you gather to ſerue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e liuing lord: they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not abide the floriſhing the truth that we deliuer faithfully, and you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ceiue obediently from vs: yea it grieueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very heart to ſee ſo many eares in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> houſe of our god, the word of god in known <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nner offered vnto you: but aboue all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich was the only thing that among and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e all ſpited theſe falſe Apoſtles to the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt) that Chriſt ſhould be preached as a full, a free Ieſus only, vnto you and among you. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d therefore our aduerſaries crie out againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> goſpell of Chriſt, that, that faith, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orketh by charitie, ſhould only bee ſaide to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ify &amp; ſaue (which is our propoſition neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re nor leſſe) for which cauſe as theſe falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tles to the diſquieting of this church of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a</hi> mingled circumciſion &amp; grace, &amp; taught <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> goſpel to be vnauaileable, vnleſſe circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were vſed as neceſſary: (by which means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y deceiued many) ſo alſo our aduerſaries do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gle workes with faith: and teach ſaluation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome not only by faith, but alſo by workes: which meanes many of the ſimple are cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>way from vs, and loſe the profite of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urs goſpel. But here, becauſe by the way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y doe except, by the way I am to aunſwere: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y except the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon not to be iuſt: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb facs="tcp:4529:12"/>
yet as theſe Apoſtles ioined together c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumciſion and Chriſt, ſo do they couple the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rites of their woorkes and Chriſt. But he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they except that circumciſion was a matter the Lawe ceremoniall, which did not, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> could not iuſtifie: but as for good woorks th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are duties of the Law morall, which both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and doe iuſtifie: but I anſwere, that indeed for circumciſion: truth it is, that it neither d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neither could execute that office: &amp; no leſſe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay of the duties of the law moral. For thou it be a principle in diuinity (confeſſed alſo our aduerſaries) that <hi>Lex impleta</hi> doth <hi>iuſt care,</hi> and <hi>iuſtificatos ſeruare</hi>) that the Law ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led doth iuſtifie and ſaue the iuſt: yet touchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the categoricall and poſitiue (whereabout queſtion is) I find it not to be true, that any doeth actually or can posſibly fulfill the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and therfore be iuſtified and ſaued by the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> But here again they except, that then god h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded things impoſſible. Wherunto I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere, that as for the imposſibility of the co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandement, it is no matter of abſurdity: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is a point of the catholicke verity taught ſcriptures, to be confeſſed by all: the Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> S. <hi>Peter</hi> in the 15. of the <hi>Acts</hi> doth witn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no leſſe, and our aduerſaries themſelues d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay no leſſe: but here again they except, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4529:12"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the place of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> it concerneth points the law ceremoniall, which was but a Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mporall: but as for good woorkes they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties of the Law moral, that bindes al men &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al ages, ſo that if the duty therof and therein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God of vs exacted, were imposſible, God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere proued a cruel &amp; rigorous God. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to I aunſwere firſt, that touching the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tualnes or temporalnes of the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, that is nothing, whence the impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eneſſe is graunted for a truth: 2 I anſwere, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at as for the duties of the law morall, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey binde perpetually and yet bee impoſſible be performed by the Godly: yet is not God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ereby proued a cruel &amp; rigorous god, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſe he demaundeth nothing but his due; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e? Yea what mans conſcience calleth duty &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nfeſſeth to bee due: now to aſke nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: yea what man cannot but confeſſe to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, that is no cruelty, no rigor but iuſtice: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d therefore to anſwere more fully: as for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties of the lawe morall, God aſketh therein thing but what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould performe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e nothing but duety: yea nothing but what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an could performe: nothing therefore but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ety: yea nothing but poſſible dutie: which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ough now hee cannot performe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re now findes the law imposſible, that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:4529:13"/>
whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he could &amp; therfore had poſſibility <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> performe it, yet he would not: ſo that that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſſibility argueth not Gods cruelty &amp; rigou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but iuſtice on his part: on our behalfe our mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerable infirmity, and yet voluntary miſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nay their owne <hi>Hugo de Victore</hi> in his an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>notations vpon this chapter ſaith that man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not loue God with all his hart, ſoule &amp;c. in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> life, and therefore is not to ſeeke ſaluation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> merites but only in grace. Wherefore to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit all large and yet eaſie apologies in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> poynt, it is flat in concluſion that our aduerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries offend no leſſe to the diſquieting of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> church now in adding woorkes morall, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did theſe falſe Apoſtles in the time of this Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle in adding woorks ceremoniall to the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell: for both waies the church findes diſquie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes: both waies chriſt is made vnprofitabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Now therefore (Deare beloued) ſith by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their legall, indeede impoſſible, and therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> no goſpell, our aduerſaries barre many a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeeke to barre you from al poſſibilitie of ſalu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: ſith all their endeuour is to make you t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Diſciples not of faith but of woorkes, not grace but of merite, not of the goſpell but the lawe, not of chriſt but of <hi>Moſes:</hi> and ſo v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the name of Ieſu do fight indeede again the glory of the Goſpel of Ieſu and ſafe
<pb facs="tcp:4529:13"/>
your ſoules: ſith there is ſuch venome, ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yſon, ſuch perill among you and for you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade by reaſon of them: ſith they the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atan buſy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues euery way to bring you this moſt miſerable ſtay &amp; piteous ſtate; oh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at ſhal I ſay but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Apoſtle, I would to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d they were cut off that thus do ſeek to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t you: oh woulde to God they were cut off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t thus diſquiet you. For you are dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in happy caſe: &amp; wher your fathers were in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t miſerable plight, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they could not, ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (the key of knowlege being take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m) knowe God and his Chriſt: yet you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w both, yea and it is our ioy to ſee you thus like of chriſt the bread of life that we diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o you: and happy are you all, to your eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing comfort we aſſure you all, that hun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> feede by faith vpon him: and I truſt that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in your owne hartes you are oft ioyfull &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry many a time to thinke vpon this our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted time, wherein you haue the foode of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſoules ſo fully &amp; freely broken vnto you. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d therefore ſith theſe euill nurſes of <hi>Rome</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k to feed you with truſt in your own works <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch you performe: and merits which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> imagin of you (which you do not, yea being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers cannot perfourme, and therfore needs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt famiſh you, if that you truſt to them) and
<pb facs="tcp:4529:14"/>
not onely of Chriſt: who yet was &amp; is the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alone loafe of life broken vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinnes, and alone by faith able and withal r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy to feede you, oh woulde to God they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cut off that thus doe ſeeke to corrupt you: woulde to God they were cutte off that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſquiet you; not that we could not wiſh th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> better: for (alas) wee know the price of ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and acknowledge the grace and good will our gracious God that way: and you can witneſſe with and for vs, that in our gener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſſemblies &amp; publique praiers we pray for ſpeedy conuerſion and ſaluation of them: na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would do our heartes good to ſee the Goat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome a Lambe: to ſee the thorn become a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there were but one fould and one ſheephea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs all: but alas be our charity neuer ſo gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wardes them: though wee pray for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when they curſe vs: though wee bleſſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> where they perſecute vs: though we preach a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> penne, take careful care euery way to diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their vntruth, that they may leaue it, to bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them to the light of the trueth that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cleaue vnto it, yet alas they condemne our c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie: they continue their wilfull race, and their trauel is how to root vp the goodly vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> yarde that God by vs hath planted amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you: day and night they watch to ſteale the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4529:14"/>
of <hi>Syon</hi> from you: they ſpite the brightneſſe the golden candleſtick of Chriſt among you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herby they ſeek the ruin of your happy eſtate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herein you now ſtand, vtterly &amp; to drown the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yce of the turtle now heard in our land: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>erfore oh what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſay, but oh would to god <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey were cut off that thus do ſeeke to greeue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: I would to god they were cut off that thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quiet you.</p>
            <p>Oh but this is no charitable wiſh you will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e. I haue aunſwered and aunſwere further, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at we wiſh them wel with al our harts: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t when we conſider the ſtifnes of them in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: yea how reſolute they are in defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reſies: &amp; how earneſtly they trauel fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> place to corrupt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that imbrace the truth: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a how they condemne and curſe true chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ans, and thirſt after nothing more then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſolation of God his holy temple among vs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her by perſuaſion, or if that preuail not, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> treacherie, force and crueltie: when I thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>member how they are &amp; wil be nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re, to trouble, yea to choke you the goodly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n of our ſauiour chriſt, &amp; how they labour &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke the paines to chaſe the poore woman a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne to the wilderneſſe, vpon whoſe breſtes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>u do now quietly take your fil of the ſincere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilk of the hony-ſweet goſpel, the very power
<pb facs="tcp:4529:15"/>
of God to ſaue your ſouls, I cannot chooſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wiſh with this our Apoſtle: oh would to G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they were cut off that doe diſquiet you. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore that wee wiſh not their conuerſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not therefore that wee wiſh not conſequent their ſaluation: not therfore that we ow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charity (as they vncharitably do ſlaunder o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> charity) but ſith they profeſſe themſelues e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies to the truth, and that they may not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> darke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but bury it, do by al meanes trauel it, you al know, &amp; this our daie is a liuely and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentable witnes, oh would to God they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cut off that ſo diſquiet you. In a woord to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clude: our harts deſire and continual praier God is, that his goſpel may haue a free cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> among you: that the light of the world may c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue with you: that the dew of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> drop vpon you: that this day of knowledge, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> day of comfort in chriſt your deare ſauior m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not be darckned againe by antichriſt: that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Doue that nowe doeth reſt in the holes of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rock (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaks) be not driuen aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to take to her wings and elſewhere to ſeek h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſt: this dearebeloued is our wiſh and dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> praier to God for you, euen that you may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thus &amp; in this comfortable &amp; happy eſtate, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gods mercy may ſtil compaſſe you &amp; his na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be glorious among you: and therefore whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4529:15"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tichriſt is abroad &amp; his Angels among vs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath euen at this verie houre moued the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wrs of the world againſt vs, who only ſpite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hope to ſpit at our peace &amp; plenty, our flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h and proſperity in the truth of our ſauior: or that cauſe ſeek not onely abroad to troble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r brethren, but euen at home to ſet <hi>Caine</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w his ſword vpon <hi>Abel:</hi> yea to ſtore our la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th troble where there is quietnes: with war <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere there is peace: with ſcarcenes, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re is plenty: with teares where there is ioy: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſtore and ſtreame our ſtreetes with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od of olde and young, man, woman &amp; childe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong vs: yea to take away the courſe of gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y word from vs: and to make this our land <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lace for that owle of <hi>Rome,</hi> that nowe is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce for the tal tree of chriſt, wherin the fouls the aire doe build their neſtes &amp; quietly reſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would to God they were cut off that thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſeeke to moleſt you: yea oh would to God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y were cut off that thus diſquiet you. Not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t you neede (deare beloued) to fear the force fleſh whatſoeuer: not that this woorld ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t you, though it neuer ſo deepely hate you: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>not <hi>Satan</hi> that prince of hel, that god of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rld (for God hath numbered the verie hairs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your heades: hee hath care ouer a ſparrow, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch more ouer you:) but becauſe wee coulde
<pb facs="tcp:4529:16"/>
wiſh that the goſpel of chriſt might ſtill run <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong you: that mother <hi>Rachel</hi> might enio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this her comfortable daie with you: that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> children might quietly ſucke vpon her breſts that neither <hi>Herod</hi> nor antichriſt might d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiet them: that ſo the trueth of Chriſt mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> triumph, and the diuel of <hi>Rome</hi> be ſtil trod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the duſt, to your great ioy heere, &amp; to your pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petuall ſafetie hereafter: in which reſpect as beegan, ſo for this time I conclude and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an end: I would to God they were cut off th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doe diſquiet you. Cut off from your compan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cut off from your congregations: cut off fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the land: cut off &amp; not permitted by fooliſh p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie and charity; yea cut off vtterly and curſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> euerlaſtingly before they ſhould either by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſy corrupt you, or by violence &amp; force ban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the truth of chriſt from amongeſt you: rath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then either of theſe ſhould fal out, I ſaie it a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaie it again and again, and that with chari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obiect what they pleaſe: oh would to God th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were cut off that do diſquiet you. Oh the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore that Papiſtes were cut off from the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for they are the traiterous and tirannous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rits of this our time, who haue &amp; ſtil do ſeek diſquiet you. God therefore look vpon vs w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the eie of his fauour, &amp; deliuer vs from the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And ſound your <hi>Amen</hi> to this concluſion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4529:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
